Okay, next discussion concerns the small bowel.
The first disorder is duodenal atresia.
Again, when you have something that's atretic, it ends in a blind loop.
And so basically the idea here is that the duodenum ends in a blind loop.
The reason why we get this is congenital,
and it's failure of the small bowel to actually canalize,
highly associated with Down syndrome.
That's a high-yield association for examination purposes.
Now the clinical features are all based on the fact that you're going to have this blind loop.
So for example, this is the esophagus, and then you've got the stomach coming off,
and then eventually you have the duodenum.
The duodenum is ending in a blind loop.
So one problem that's going to occur is polyhydramnios.
Now polyhydramnios means too much amniotic fluid.
Remember that the amniotic fluid, the major component, is generated from the urine of the baby,
so that the urine of the baby is the major component of the amniotic fluid.
And at the same time, the way by which we resorb some of that amniotic fluid
is by swallowing it and digesting it,
so that the baby is swallowing and digesting amniotic fluid,
and that helps to decrease the volume of amniotic fluid.
If we don't have that physiologic swallowing and digesting,
we're going to get too much amniotic fluid, or polyhydramnios.
And of course, in this particular case, the babies can bring in a little bit of that amniotic fluid,
but they can't pass it through the rest of the gut.
So this would be one problem that could arise in these babies.
Another problem is that they get bilious vomiting,
and the idea here is that as you get building up of the food within this tract,
of course it ends in a blind loop,
and of course the bile is coming in from the duodenum,
and so this is going to end up being regurgitated out,
and that's going to result in vomiting,
and it'll be bilious because it's got bile coming in at the level of the duodenum.
So that's an important clinical feature.
And the third important clinical feature is that you're going to get distension of the stomach,
and you're also going to get distension of the duodenum.
And in between here is the pyloric sphincter, which is going to remain tight.
And so that's going to produce two separate areas of distension,
and that is called the double bubble sign.
It's best visualized by imaging.
So here you've got the stomach, for example.
There's a tightening here where you have the pyloric sphincter,
and then here you've got the duodenum,
so two bubbles, bubble number one and then bubble number two,
double bubble sign, very high yield for examination purposes.
Meckel's diverticulum, remember that a diverticulum is an outpouching of a wall.
That's the first point.
And in this particular case, you get outpouching of all of the layers of the ball wall.
So that's called a true diverticulum.
Remember that you can also have false diverticulums.
For example, the one diverticulum that we've covered in this chapter so far
was a Zenker's diverticulum,
in which you had outpouching of the mucosa through the muscle wall,
or through the muscle layer.
And so that was a false diverticulum.
This is a true diverticulum,
and it's one of the few true diverticulums that we're going to study.
Now this arises embryologically due to a failure of the vitalin duct to involute.
Let's talk about the vitalin duct for a moment.
Remember that in early embryonic development,
the midgut actually receives its nutrients from the yolk sac.
So early in life, when we're developing the baby or the fetus,
the midgut is actually going to receive its nutrients from the yolk sac.
And the way by which it receives those nutrients is via the vitalin duct.
So we could say that the vitalin duct is vital for receiving nutrients during early development.
This duct normally forms in about the fourth week.
It then involutes by about the seventh week of gestation.
And if you have persistence of the duct,
that results in something called a Meckel's diverticulum.
So it's really persistence of the vitalin duct.
It's interesting, you can have a couple problems here.
One problem is that you can have the fact that the duct does not involute at all,
and that would result in the passing of meconium via the umbilicus at birth.
So if they gave you an examination question in which the patient is passing meconium via the umbilicus,
that means that there was failure of the vitalin duct to resolve completely,
meaning that there was no resorption or no involution of that duct at all.
But it's also possible that you can get a slight closing of that duct,
but it fails to involute completely,
and that would result in something called a Meckel's diverticulum.
One of the interesting things that may be seen, especially on examination,
when you do a clinical exam on these patients,
is you can kind of feel the umbilical area, and it feels like there's stool.
It feels like there's something firm but soft,
or something solid but soft within the umbilical area,
and that's because there's stool caught up in the Meckel's diverticulum.
So that's an important, interesting finding as well.
Now, this is what the Meckel's diverticulum looks like.
This is basically the diverticulum here.
It's an outpouching coming off the intestine,
and the intestine, of course, would be running this way.
Now, there's some rules of twos that are highly associated with the Meckel's,
and you do need to be familiar with them.
They help you to remember some of the important clinical and epidemiologic features.
Number one, it's seen in 2% of the population.
It's the most common congenital anomaly of the GI tract.
It's usually 2 inches long, and it's usually located in the small bowel,
about 2 feet from the ileocecal valve.
And again, by here, you can imagine that this would be 2 inches long.
So those are the rules of twos.
There's a few more.
First of all, this usually occurs, usually it's asymptomatic,
but if it does present, it can present within the first two years of life.
And the way by which it can present includes bleeding, volvulus,
and a volvulus is where you get a twisting of the bowel on its mesentery.
It can present with intussusception,
and intussusception is when you get telescoping of the bowel,
or it can present with obstruction.
This bleeding is particularly important,
and that's because you need to know that within a Meckel's eye reticulum,
you can also have heterotopic gastric mucosa.
Now, that gastric mucosa would produce acid,
and then you'd get acidic damage to the Meckel's eye reticulum,
which would then present as bleeding.
All right, next disorder is a volvulus.
This is when you get twisting of the bowel along its mesentery.
Now, remember that if you've got bowel,
the blood supply is coming in through the mesentery.
So if you twist the bowel along its mesentery,
you're going to create two problems.
Number one, you're going to obstruct the bowel,
and number two, you're going to disrupt the blood supply.
And of course, a disruption of blood supply will result in infarction.
Now, the most common locations are those locations
where you have a ton of mesentery,
so that there's some redundancy that allows for this twisting.
So in the elderly, the classic location is the sigmoid colon.
And in the young adult, the classic location is the cecum.
Here's what a volvulus looks like.
Basically, this area here has been twisted,
and this area is normal, and this area is normal as well.
And so when this twisted, there was infarction of that area,
and you can clearly see that this is a hemorrhagic infarction of the bowel.
Now, intussusception refers to telescoping of a proximal segment of bowel
into the distal segment.
Now, here's basically the idea.
Let's pretend that this is the bowel, and the flow is moving this way.
The idea is that you kind of drag in the bowel along the direction of flow,
along the direction of peristalsis.
So that's called intussusception,
the telescoping of a proximal segment into a distal segment.
Now, what's important to note about intussusception is that,
obviously, when you drag in the bowel,
you're going to be dragging in the blood supply as well.
And so that dragging in of the blood supply is going to result in infarction.
And these patients classically present with obstruction or with infarction,
and that infarction can often present itself with something called current jelly stools.
Now, it's important to note that whenever you have intussusception,
usually it's associated with a leading edge.
Now, remember I said that basically it's in the direction of peristalsis.
So there's got to be something that the peristalsis can kind of hook on
and grab the bowel and drag it forward.
And so you want to ask yourself the question when you have an intussusception is,
what was the underlying cause that allowed the bowel to get dragged forward?
And in children, the most common cause is lymphoid hyperplasia.
So remember that there are a ton of perist patches within the intestine,
and those perist patches are particularly prevalent within the terminal ilium.
So the idea is the patient gets some sort of,
or the child gets some sort of viral infection,
they get massive lymphoid hyperplasia,
and the terminal ilium gets dragged into the cecum because of the thickness of its wall.
In adults, you'd classically think about tumor as being the leading edge
that allows for an intussusception to occur.
Small bowel infarction,
we should know that the small bowel is very susceptible to ischemic injury.
Remember that the small bowel needs a lot of ATP
because it's doing a ton of digestion.
It does a lot of the absorption
and a lot of the digestion necessary to be able to bring nutrients into the body.
And so it's going to be highly susceptible to ischemic injury.
Now when you get ischemia of the small bowel,
there's a couple possibilities of what could occur.
One possibility is that you can get a transmural infarction.
And this is going to occur,
let's pretend that this is the bowel and this is the blood supply coming in,
and this is the blood supply coming out.
So you've got an artery and you've got a vein.
Now, transmural infarction is going to occur
when you get thrombosis or embolism of the artery,
and it's got to be the superior mesenteric artery,
or if you get thrombosis of the vein.
It's kind of that same paradigm that we keep talking about.
Now let's ask a couple questions.
How would we get embolism of the artery?
Well, one way by which we could get embolism would be
if the patient has atrial fib.
Remember, if the patient has atrial fibrillation,
then basically the idea would be that they can develop a thrombus
because of the lack of motility of the atrium,
and that thrombus could break off and then embolize,
and that would be called a thromboembolist,
and that could lodge itself in the SMA and then create an infarction.
The other possibility would be that the patient, for example, has a vasculitis.
And so if the patient gets a vasculitis,
that can increase the risk for thrombosis and subsequent infarction.
For example, one classic example would be polyarteritis nodosa,
in which the patient's actually had melanoma and abdominal pain.
And if you go back and review polyarteritis nodosa,
you'll see that one of the features was abdominal complaints.
And then the third way would be to get thrombosis of the mesenteric vein.
And how would you get thrombosis of the mesenteric vein?
Well, one classic mechanism would be something called polycythemia vera,
where you have a red blood cell disorder,
where you're producing too many red blood cells,
which makes the blood thick and increases the risk for thrombosis.
Another classic example would be if the patient has a lupus anticoagulant.
That would increase the risk for thrombosis as well.
So in these particular cases, when you're going to block the blood supply,
that's going to result in a transmural infarction so that the entire wall gets infarcted.
Now the other possibility is that you can get a mucosal infarction.
And the way that by which that would occur is that if you've got this blood supply going to the wall,
and you've got a mucosa and a submucosa, etc., and here's the blood supply,
imagine that you don't cut the blood supply completely, but that you decrease it slightly.
If you decrease it slightly, then the mucosa, which is furthest away from the blood supply,
would actually become ischemic, and you'd get infarction only of the mucosa.
And that occurs when you have marked hypotension.
So when there's hypotension, then you can get mucosal infarction
instead of a complete transmural infarction.
The clinical features, of course, will be abdominal pain with bloody diarrhea.
These are the key features of infarction, and there will also be decreased bowel sounds
as the bowel becomes less active.
The next disorder we want to discuss is lactose intolerance.
This is due to a decreased function of the lactase enzyme
that's present in the brush border of the enterocytes.
Before we can understand this, we need to do a little review of physiology.
Let's remind ourselves that one of the nutrients that we want to take from the gut
and bring into the blood is going to be sugar or carbohydrates.
Remember that carbohydrates are broken down into oligosaccharides by the amylases
in the salivary gland and the pancreas, and also into disaccharides,
such as lactose and sucrose.
Now, eventually, you can only absorb monosaccharides,
and so you've got to break down all of those oligosaccharides,
and you've got to break down the lactose and the sucrose as well into monosaccharides.
And remember from biochemistry that there are three monosaccharides
that are going to be absorbed, glucose, galactose, and fructose.
Now, in order to break down lactose, we have an enzyme present on the brush border
of our enterocytes, which line the small bowel, and that is called lactase.
And you need this lactase enzyme to break down lactose.
If there is a decreased function of the lactase enzyme,
then what's going to happen is that the lactose will remain
within the lumen of the small bowel, and lactose is osmotically active.
It will draw water towards it, and that will create a diarrhea.
So how will these patients present?
They present with abdominal distension and diarrhea when they consume milk products,
and that's because milk products contain a ton of lactose.
Now, when you get deficiency, it can be congenital or acquired.
The congenital deficiency is rare.
It would basically be a child who was born without the enzyme.
That's super rare.
You can also get acquired deficiency, and acquired deficiency occurs in two ways.
One way by which patients get acquired deficiency is simply as they age,
they just become intolerant, and this classically would occur, for example, in a child,
so maybe a 10-year-old, 15-year-old child who was normal up to that age,
and then all of a sudden becomes lactose intolerant.
And, of course, they would be lactose intolerant for the rest of their life.
Another acquired way to get lactose intolerant would be after any GI infection.
When you get a GI tract infection, for example, a viral infection of the small bowel,
that can destroy the enzyme, and therefore the patients can become lactose intolerant,
but, of course, that would be temporary until the small bowel would actually heal.
The next disorder is celiac disease.
This is immune-mediated damage of the small bowel villi, so that's the key thing.
You're going to knock out the small bowel villi, and it's due to gluten exposure.
Basically, this is a hypersensitivity.
There is an antigen out in the environment that, when it hits the bowel,
results in destruction of the small bowel villi.
It is associated with HLA-DQ2 and HLA-DQ8.
Now, the key component that is going to result in this hypersensitivity is something called gluten,
and gluten is present in wheat and grains and is in very many foods that we consume.
The most pathologic component of gluten, you have to know for examination purposes, is gliadin,
and you also need to know that gliadin gets deamidated.
Now, when this occurs, it occurs by a tissue transglutaminase.
Now, this changed or altered gliadin is then grabbed by the antigen-presenting cells
and then presented via MHC class II to the helper T cells,
and it's the helper T cells that mediate the tissue damage.
So, it's the T cells that are creating the problem here.
Now, clinically, this can have a very broad presentation,
but the classic finding in children would be abdominal distension, diarrhea, and failure to thrive,
and in adults, it would be chronic diarrhea and bloating.
So, these are the ways by which we would classically see a presentation of this particular disorder.
Now, one associated finding is something called dermatitis repetiformis,
and the idea here is that if we draw a picture of skin,
now, this is the epidermis up here,
all right, so this is the epidermis,
and underneath it is the dermis,
and remember that we have dermal papillae here.
Now, recall that the blood supply of the skin is all in the dermis.
There are no blood vessels in the epidermis.
So, as blood vessels come up here,
now, one of the things that can happen in this disorder
is you can get deposition of IgA at the tips of these dermal papillae.
Now, the deposition of IgA at the tips of the dermal papillae
will result in destruction of the connection
between the epidermis and the dermis at that point,
so that what you'll get is a little blister or vesicle right here
at the tip of the dermal papillae,
and then you'll get another tiny little vesicle here,
and then another tiny vesicle at the dermal papillae here.
Now, these are little tiny vesicles, so they look like herpes,
and so that's why it's called herpetiformis.
You get very similar herpes looking like blisters,
and so what's important to note is that it's due to IgA deposition
at the tips of the dermal papillae,
and that it resolves with a gluten-free diet.
Now, the laboratory findings are that you get IgA antibodies
against a few things.
Number one, endomysium.
Endomysium is the connective tissue
that ensheets each individual muscle fiber.
In this particular disorder, there is no problem with the endomysium,
but it so happens that they develop antibodies against endomysium,
and so that's one thing we can test for.
They also can get IgA against tissue transglutaminase,
or IgA against gliadin.
So these are the classic laboratory findings.
Now, what's interesting about patients with celiac disease
is that a subset of these patients can be IgA deficient.
Remember that when we talked about IgA deficiency in your immune lecture,
I mentioned at that point that there's an increased incidence of IgA deficiency
in patients with celiac disease.
And so if they're IgA deficient,
then you're not going to be able to find the IgA antibodies.
And so it's also important to test for IgG antibodies
because those would be useful for diagnosis
in patients that have an IgA deficiency.
Obviously, if you have an IgA deficiency,
you won't have IgA against these particular antigens.
And so in those patients, we want to look for IgG antibodies
against, for example, tissue transglutaminase.
This is just one example.
Now, the way by which we make the diagnosis
is also to do a duodenal biopsy.
The biopsy will show flattening of the villi
and hyperplasia of the crypts.
Let's go back and remind ourselves
that this is the small bowel surface.
You've got these villi that go up,
and you've got these tiny crypts that come down.
So villi that go up, and then tiny crypts that come down.
Now, what happens in this disorder
is you get flattening of these villi,
so you're going to lose these villi.
You're going to get hyperplasia of these crypts,
so the crypts are going to become deeper,
and then you're going to see lymphocytes
within the epithelium.
So you get an increased number
of intraepithelial lymphocytes.
And here's what it looks like.
You've got flattening.
Here's the surface.
There are no villi,
so you've got flattening of the villi,
but you've got hyperplasia of these crypts,
and then you've got all these lymphocytes present.
Now, in particular, you would see them
within the epithelium up here.
Now, this is the normal histology,
just to remind you that
you normally should have these nice, tall villi,
and then these crypts should be very minimal.
All right, and so, again,
we're losing all of these villi in celiac disease.
Now, one more important point
that I make here in the notes,
and that is the distribution,
which is super high yield.
The damage is mostly in the duodenum,
and the jejunum and ilium are less involved.
I can't repeat that enough.
Remember that the damage is mostly in the duodenum,
and the jejunum and ilium are less involved.
All right, of course, as I've already mentioned,
the symptoms resolve if you put the patient
on a gluten-free diet.
Now, let's say that on an examination in particular,
the patient's on a gluten-free diet for many years,
and they swear up and down
that they've been maintaining that diet.
Now, all of a sudden, they start getting disease.
Again, refractory disease,
despite the fact that they claim good dietary control,
and they've had good dietary control for several years.
Then you need to think about two particular complications
that could be leading to this refractory disease.
The first would be that the patient
could have developed small bowel carcinoma.
So there's an increased risk
for development of small bowel carcinoma
in patients with celiac disease,
especially with long-standing celiac disease.
And then second, it's a possibility
that the patient developed a lymphoma.
But what's interesting here
is that these patients can develop a T-cell lymphoma.
And that's kind of rare
because we haven't talked about many T-cell lymphomas.
We've talked about a lot of B-cell lymphomas
throughout this course.
And so it's important to know
that these patients can develop a T-cell lymphoma.
And that T-cell lymphoma is also called EATL,
E-A-T-L.
And that stands for
Enteropathy Associated T-cell Lymphoma.
But anyway, I think the most important thing
for you to note is that
if there's refractory disease,
think about cancer, think about lymphoma,
and in particular, a T-cell lymphoma.
Now, tropical sprue is another disorder
that's very similar
in that you get damage to the small bowel villi.
And when you get damage to the small bowel villi,
in this particular case,
it's due to an unknown organism.
Of course, it results in malabsorption.
Whenever you knock out the villi,
you're gonna get malabsorption and diarrhea.
Now, this is very similar to celiac disease
with a couple exceptions.
Exception number one,
it occurs in tropical regions like the Caribbean.
And of course,
that's because it's due to some infectious agent,
and that's where the infectious agent
tends to be located.
Now, number two,
it arises after infectious diarrhea.
So, you clearly have an infection,
and then the patient develops this tropical sprue.
And it also responds to antibiotics,
indicating that it's being driven
by this infectious agent.
But here's the super high yield point
that I wanna make.
And that is that in tropical sprue,
the damage is more in the jejunum and the ileum,
whereas in celiac disease,
the damage was more in the duodenum.
But the duodenum is less commonly involved
in tropical sprue.
So, the predominant disease
is in the jejunum and the ileum.
Now, because the disease
is predominantly in the jejunum and the ileum,
you can also get nutritional deficiencies
based on what is occurring
in the jejunum and the ileum.
So, remember that in the jejunum,
that is the key place
where we absorb folic acid.
So, we can get folic acid deficiency.
And also, the ileum is the key place
where we absorb vitamin B12.
So, we can potentially develop,
theoretically develop,
a vitamin B12 deficiency.
Okay.
Next disorder is called Whipple's disease.
This is a systemic disease
in which you get macrophages
loaded with T. whippelli organisms.
Okay, what's the idea here?
The patient gets a T. whippelli infection.
The macrophages begin to eat away
at the T. whippelli,
trying to kill them.
But instead of killing them,
they can only partially destroy them.
And because they can only partially destroy them,
the organism remains within
the macrophage lysosomes.
And so, that's an important consideration
because in this disorder,
you're going to get tons of macrophages
loaded with the bugs.
Now, the classic site of involvement
is the lamina propria of the small bowel.
And that's very important
because that's then going to lead
to the classic symptoms of this disorder,
which is fat malabsorption and steatorrhea.
But before we can understand that,
we need to take a little step back.
So, let's remind ourselves
that when you think about the small bowel,
you've got these villi, correct?
And the villi have these enterocytes.
And the enterocytes are sitting
on a lamina propria.
The connective tissue of the villus
is called a lamina propria.
So, that's the first point that I want to make.
Now, I'm going to go back and draw that
with that background in mind.
So, you've got these enterocytes
and then you've got the lamina propria.
Now, let's talk a little bit about fat digestion.
So, lipids are obviously broken down
by lipases from the salaried gland
and lipases from the pancreas.
And then they're emulsified into smaller droplets
in the stomach and the small bowel.
And bile, of course, helps
in that emulsification process.
The end result is the production of a micelle
that easily diffuses across the cellular membrane,
which then brings in the fatty acids
into the enterocyte.
And once you have fatty acid within the enterocyte,
then the next thing that's going to happen
is you're going to repackage those fatty acids
into chylomicrons.
Now, chylomicrons are relatively big molecules
and they're going to come out into the lamina propria.
They can't go into the blood.
And when they go into the lamina propria,
they're going to be resorbed
in these small little lymphatic spaces called lacteals.
So, the chylomicrons are going to be brought in
to these lacteals.
And then, of course, they go into the lacteals,
into the lymphatics,
and the lymphatics eventually drain
via the thoracic duct into the blood.
So, that's the way by which the chylomicrons
are brought into the blood.
They can't go directly into the blood.
They have to go into the lymphatics
and then eventually they land in the blood
because of their size.
Now, what's going to happen in this particular disorder,
which is Whipple's disease,
is that you're going to get a ton of macrophages.
So, let's just make them with squares, okay?
You get a ton of macrophages present
within this lamina propria.
Now, all those macrophages are going to pile up
and they're going to eventually compress
these thin-walled lacteals.
So, if you compress these thin-walled lacteals,
you can't bring the chylomicrons in anymore.
And if you can't bring in the chylomicrons,
the patients are going to get a fat malabsorption.
And that's exactly the mechanism by which they get
fat malabsorption and steatorrhea.
All right, here's what it looks like.
This is the small bowel villus here.
All right, and these are the enterocytes here.
And you can see that there's all these foamy macrophages
within the lamina propria,
as I've just sort of outlined.
Again, foamy macrophages in the lamina propria.
Now, I could prove that these are macrophages
loaded with the organisms
by doing a special stain called a PAS stain,
which would show me the little organisms.
And this dark pink material within the macrophages
indicates that I'm actually dealing with Whipple's disease
because I can clearly see the little fragments
of the organisms.
Now, remember that this is a systemic disease,
so that the most common site
is the lamina propria of the small bowel.
But it can also involve the joints giving you arthritis,
in particular the synovium,
the cardiac valves, the lymph nodes, and the CNS.
So that's something to bear in the back of your mind.
The next disorder that we're going to talk about
is A-beta lipoproteinemia.
A means without,
and this is without your beta lipoproteins.
Now, the idea here is that you get
an autosomal recessive deficiency
of apolipoprotein B48 and B100.
Now, what's B48 important for?
You need B48 to make the chylomicron.
So if you can't make the chylomicron,
you can't absorb fat,
and they're going to get a malabsorption.
At the same time, you need B100
to be able to produce your VLDL and your LDL,
and so therefore, these patients are going to have
absent plasma VLDL and LDL.
All right, moving along,
we're going to talk about carcinoid tumor.
Carcinoid tumor is a malignant proliferation
of neuroendocrine cells.
It's a low-grade malignancy.
Now, let's remind ourselves
that when you think about tumors
of neuroendocrine cells,
you can kind of have a spectrum.
The worst tumor in the highest grade
and the worst tumor of a neuroendocrine cell
is called small cell carcinoma,
and that occurred in the lung,
and we've already talked about it,
but remember that sort of the lowest form
of malignancy of a neuroendocrine cell
is called a carcinoid tumor.
Now, a carcinoid tumor,
it's important to note
that those tumors are neuroendocrine,
and so they're going to be filled
with neuroendocrine granules,
and very high yield that shows up on exams often
is the fact that these tumor cells
will be positive for an immunohistochemical stain
called chromogranin.
This is very high yield.
It likes to show up on exams.
So neuroendocrine tumors,
in particular the carcinoid tumor,
but this would also be true
of a small cell carcinoma of the lung,
would be positive for chromogranin.
Now, carcinoid tumors can occur
anywhere along the gut,
but the small bowel is the most common site.
The way I remember that
is to remind myself that every site has cancer.
For example, in esophagus,
we talked about esophageal cancer.
In the stomach, we talked about stomach cancer.
When we do the colon,
we'll talk about colon cancer,
but there really is no common small bowel cancer.
Remember that I told you earlier in our discussion
that small bowel carcinoma is very rare.
And so the way I remember this
is that we've got to give the small bowel something,
and so we'll give it the carcinoid tumor.
So it's sort of just, I don't know,
a funny way to remember something
that you do need to know.
Now, these normally grow
as submucosal polyp-like nodules,
and this is what it looks like.
You get these little raised protrusions
that are actually submucosal,
but are creating these little polyps.
Now, they often secrete serotonin,
and this is very important.
So when you have a carcinoid tumor,
what's going to happen is,
let's pretend that this is the tumor,
the tumor is going to dump into the portal vein,
and when it dumps into the portal vein,
that is going to feed to the liver.
And so when it feeds to the liver,
then the liver is going to process that serotonin, right?
Because, let's start over,
the tumor secretes serotonin,
dumps it into the portal vein,
the portal vein will then send it to the liver,
in the liver it will be processed
by an enzyme called monoamine oxidase, MAO.
Monoamine oxidase will break down the serotonin
into 5-HIAA, which is a metabolite of serotonin,
and that will then be excreted in the urine.
Now, this is very important
because when these tumors secrete serotonin,
the only thing you're going to have at this point
is an increase in 5-HIAA.
There will not be carcinoid syndrome.
Carcinoid syndrome requires that the serotonin
go into the systemic circuit.
However, in this particular case,
all of the serotonin has been destroyed by the liver.
Now, let's pretend that this carcinoid tumor
metastasizes so that now the carcinoid tumor itself
spreads to the liver.
So here's the carcinoid tumor.
It's now metastatic into the liver.
Well, once it's metastatic into the liver,
now the carcinoid tumor can dump its serotonin
into the hepatic vein.
And when it dumps the serotonin into the hepatic vein,
it's important to note that the hepatic vein
has tiny connections with the systemic circuit
so that now this serotonin can actually get
into the systemic circuit and hit places
such as the lung and the skin
and create the classic picture of carcinoid syndrome,
which again is defined as bronchospasm,
diarrhea, and flushing of the skin.
All right, so it's important to note a general principle
that only when you have metastasis to the liver
will you actually get the carcinoid syndrome.
I can't emphasize that enough.
Now at the same time, because you've got metastasis to the liver
and you're dumping it to the hepatic vein,
the hepatic vein will eventually feed into the right heart
via the vena cava.
And when you get serotonin hitting the right heart,
that's going to create fibrosis of the heart valves,
and that's called carcinoid heart disease.
So again, I'd like to highlight one central principle,
and that is you don't get carcinoid syndrome
and you don't get carcinoid heart disease
until the tumor actually metastasizes to the liver.
Carcinoid syndrome, of course, is bronchospasm,
diarrhea, and flushing of the skin.
These symptoms can be triggered
by drinking of alcohol or emotional stress.
Both alcohol and emotional stress
can actually cause release of the hormone,
of the serotonin from the tumor.
At the same time, the patients can get carcinoid heart disease
when there is metastasis of the carcinoid tumor
to the liver,
and that's going to result in a right-sided valvular fibrosis.
It's important to note that the notion here
is that you're going to get deposition of collagen
within the valves.
That deposition of collagen within the valves
can lead to tricuspid regurgitation
and pulmonary valve stenosis.
So those are the two key complications.
Now let me just make one point here very clear
because it's also high yield for board examinations,
and that is you don't get left-sided valvular disease.
And the reason you don't get left-sided valvular disease
is because when the serotonin goes into the right heart,
it'll then get pumped into the lung,
and the lung also has monoamine oxidase.
Very important, very high yield.
The lung also has monoamine oxidase,
and therefore patients won't get left-sided valvular fibrosis
because the serotonin will have been converted
to 5-HIAA before it gets to the left side of the heart.
All right, so you won't get left-sided valvular fibrosis.
And that closes off our discussion on small bowel.
Have a great day of life.
Let's wait for years todop.
Let's wait for years not to kill.
All right, so Paul is not my nephew.
Please keep seeing uzk と that samequeаци dessus.